<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Kings edict and declaration vpon the former edicts of pacification Published in Paris at the parliament held the xxv. of Februarie. 1599. At Paris, by the printers and stationers ordinary to the King. 1599. Cum priuilegio dictæ Maiestatis.</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1598-04-03</title>
            <author>France. Sovereign (1589-1610 : Henry IV)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02979</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103955</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839697</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839697</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4143</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02979)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4143)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 322:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Kings edict and declaration vpon the former edicts of pacification Published in Paris at the parliament held the xxv. of Februarie. 1599. At Paris, by the printers and stationers ordinary to the King. 1599. Cum priuilegio dictæ Maiestatis.</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1598-04-03</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1589-1610 : Henry IV)</author>
                  <author>Henry IV, King of France, 1553-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>66, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R[ichard] F[ield] for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Edict of Nantes. This version has 94 articles.</note>
                  <note>Dated: Nantz in the moneth of Aprill .. 1598.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Huguenots --  France --  Legal status, laws, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4143:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4143:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE KINGS EDICT AND DECLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATION VPON THE FORMER Edicts of Pacification.</p>
            <p>PVBLISHED IN PARIS AT THE PARLIAMENT HELD <hi>the xxv. of Februarie.</hi> 1599.</p>
            <p>AT PARIS, By the Printers and Stationers ordinary to the King. 1599.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio dictae Maieſtatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by R. F. for Thomas Man. 1599.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:4143:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4143:2"/>
            <head>THE KINGS EDICT AND DECLARATION VPON THE FORMER EDICTS OF PACIFICATION.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Enrie</hi> by the grace of God, king of <hi>Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Nauarre,</hi> to all that are preſent and to come, greeting. Amongſt the infinit benefits which it hath pleaſed God to beſtow vpon vs, this may well be accounted and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed as one of the moſt rare and notable, namely that it hath pleaſed him to giue vs the grace and power to vndergo and beare out the hideous and dreadfull monſter of troubles, confuſions, and diſorders, which were rife and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed this whole Realme at our comming to the Crowne, as being then deuided into ſo many parties and factions, and that in ſuch ſort, as that the moſt loyall and naturall part, was in a maner the leaſt: and withall in ſuch ſort to haue oppoſed and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs againſt ſuch boyſtrous blaſts of ſtormie tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, as that we haue in the end ouerrid and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, arriuing at the length in the hauen of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4143:3"/> the ſafe deliuerance and peaceable quietnes of this eſtate. Of all which let God haue the whole and onely praiſe and glorie, and we ſo ſtirred vp, prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and bound to him thereby, as that we may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſurceaſe or giue ouer the offering vp of our ſelf, in all the beſt maner of ſeruice we can, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting &amp; ful accompliſhing of this worthie worke: wherin his hand and power hath bene moſt clearely and manifeſtly, ſhewing it ſelfe vnto the ſight of all men, giuing vs to beare and vndergo, not onely ſo much as our place and abilitie did require, but much more and farre aboue the ſame; and that in ſuch ſort and meaſure, as (our dignitie conſidered) in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other time would haue bene verie vnmeete and inconuenient: as neuer fearing to hazard therein our princely renowne, by the free expoſing of our limmes and life ſo oft vnto ſo many dangerous oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences accompanying the ſame. But now where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we haue found it vnpoſſible to ſettle and bring into good order ſo confuſed a heape and multitude of ſo great, ſo weightie, and ſo dangerous affaires and buſineſſes at once, and at one time: we haue thought good to take this courſe, namely to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in the firſt place, ſuch things as could not but by force &amp; might be atchieued, reſeruing for a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time the other, which ought and might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by reaſon and courſe of iuſtice. As (for example) the generall quarrels that then raigned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our good ſubiects, and the particular miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs and iniuries lying vpon the ſoundeſt and moſt truſty parties of our kingdome, all which we iudged
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4143:3"/> much more eaſie to be redreſſed and cured, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ciuill warres (the originall &amp; cauſe of continuance of the ſame) ſhould be cut off and taken away. Now we hauing (by Gods aſſiſting hand) wel and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſlie preuayled herein, to the vtter extirpation of warres and all maner of hoſtility out of all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and quarters of our realme, we hope with as good ſucceſſe to compoſe and ſet in order the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as yet out of ſquare and order, that ſo we may attaine the full eſtabliſhment of a firme peace and ſetled quietneſſe, which hath alwaies bene the ſcope and drift of all our deſires and reſolutions; and the price we aymed at in al the paines and trauels which we haue vndertake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> throughout the whole courſe of our life. Now amongſt the affaires and matters with patience and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance of time to be remedied (&amp; that one of the chiefeſt and moſt principall thereof) were the complaints, which we receiued from many of our prouinces and Catholike townes, for that the exerciſes of the Catholike religion, were not gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally again eſtabliſhed, according to the Edicts here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore made for the pacifying of the troubles, which had riſen and ſprong from the cauſe of Religion. As alſo the ſupplications and admonitions offred vnto vs by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the pretended reformed religion, as well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the default &amp; lacke of due execution done of that which hath bene granted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by vertue of the aforeſaid Edicts, as alſo for that they deſired, that there might furthermore be added vnto the ſaid Edicts, the eſtabliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the exerciſes of their ſaid Religion, the liberty of their conſciences, &amp; the ſafty
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4143:4"/> and ſecuritie of their perſons and goods, preſuming that they had iuſt matter to draw them to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining of ſome new and great conceits, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the laſt troubles and diſturbances, alleaging that the principall drift and occaſion thereof, was plotted and layed to entrap and wholy to ouertread them. Which things (that we might not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our ſelfe with multitudes of buſineſſes at one time, as alſo in aſmuch as the raging heat of warres did gainſay and hold out all eſtabliſhment of lawes, (how good, wholſome, and neceſſarie ſoeuer they might haue bene) we haue ſtill deferred from time to time to prouide for. But now, ſeeing it pleaſeth God to giue vs to inioy ſome better quietneſſe and reſt, we haue iudged that the ſame cannot better be imployed, then to make it our leiſure and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, to reſpect and take in hand the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his glorie and holie worſhip, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide that he may be honoured and ſerued of all our ſubiects: and that (though it pleaſe him not to haue it after one maner of forme, and in one kind of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, it may be at the leaſt to one and the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and with ſuch a cariage, as may be free from all maner of troubles and tumults that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would riſe amongſt them; and that we and this our Realme may euermore deſerue and conſerue the glorious title of <hi>Moſt Chriſtian,</hi> which hath ſo long ſince for ſo manifold our merits &amp; deſerts bene purchaſed and obtained; and by the ſame meanes take away the cauſe of miſchiefe and trouble, which may riſe vpon the matter of religion, as being the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4143:4"/> thing that alwayes moueth the heart and eyes more then all other things beſides. For this cauſe we (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing conſidered the waightineſſe of the matter, and that it deſerueth with all carefulneſſe to be looked into, and hauing againe receiued the humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts and ſupplications of our Catholike ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, as alſo hauing permitted our ſaid ſubiects of the pretended reformed Religion, to aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by their Deputies to make theirs ready, and to incloſe together and ſhut vp in one, what they haue to ſay or alleage for themſelues, and about the ſame matter to conferre with them diuerſe times; and hauing further peruſed the ſaid former Edicts throughly) haue thought it meet to frame a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, plaine, vpright or indifferent and abſolute law concerning the whole matter, in the behalfe of all our ſubiects, that by it they may be ruled in ſuch controuerſies, as heretofore haue riſen amongſt them hereby, or which hereafter might riſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them, and whereby both the one and the other may find matter to content the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues withall, as far forth as the time (conſidered as it is) will beare. And this our reſolution and mature deliberation, we haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken nothing at all in reſpect of our ſelfe, but in reſpect onely of the zeale which we haue for to ſee God ſerued: and that it may from henceforth make, procure, and eſtabliſh amongſt our ſubiects a ſound and laſting peace. For the which we beſeech and ſtill waite vpon his diuine Maieſtie, crauing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the like protection and fauour, which he hath continually in moſt cleare and manifeſt ſort
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4143:5"/> vouchſafed this Realme, from ſince the time it firſt was, and throughout all that long tract of time that it hath continued: &amp; that it wold likewiſe pleaſe his Maieſtie to ſhew our ſubiects ſuch fauor and grace, as that they may learne to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of this our ordinance, conſiſteth (next to that which they owe to God and to vs) the principal foundation of their vnitie and concord, tranquility and reſt, and of the entire reeſtabliſhing of this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in his former glorie, wealth, and mightineſſe. And as for our ſelfe, we promiſe to cauſe it to be exactly obſerued, without tollerating or bearing with any maner of encounter or reſiſtance. For theſe cauſes hauing (with the aduiſe of the Princes of our bloud, &amp; other Princes &amp; officers vnto the Crowne, and other great &amp; notable perſonages of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Eſtate, being about vs) well and diligently weighed and conſidered all the whole matter, we haue by this our perpetuall and irreuocable Decree pronounced, declared, &amp; ordained, do pronounce, declare, and ordaine:</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>Firſt, that the remembrance of all things paſſed of the one part and of the other, from the beginning of the moneth of March in the yeare 1585. vnto our comming to the Crowne, and during the other troubles going before, and by the occaſion of them, ſhal remaine for dead and buried, and as things that neuer were. And it ſhall not be lawfull or permitted vnto any of our Atturneyes generall, or any other perſons whatſoeuer, publike or priuate, at any time,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4143:5"/> vpon any occaſion that may happen, to make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therof, or to implead or accuſe any for the ſame in any of our Courts or iuriſdictions whatſoeuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>We forbid likewiſe all our ſubiects, of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or quality ſoeuer they be, to renew the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance aforeſaid, by multiplying of words, by ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macking, wronging, or prouoking of one another, with the reproch of anie thing that is paſt, vpon anie cauſe, pretext, or colour whatſoeuer, in diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, proteſtations, or any maner of quarels, neither yet to miſcall or offend by word one another, about anie word or deed before paſt: but to containe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and to liue peacebly together as brethren, friends, and fellow citizens, vpon paine for offending herein, to be puniſhed as breakers of the peace, and diſturbers of the publike quietneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>We ordaine, that the Catholike, Apoſtolike, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Religion ſhall be reſtored and eſtabliſhed againe in all the places of this our Realme &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries vnder our iuriſdiction, where the exerciſe of the ſame hath bene neglected, there to be freely and peacebly exerciſed without any maner of moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or impeachment. Forbidding moſt expreſly all maner of perſons of what eſtate, quality, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition ſoeuer they be, vpon the penaltie aboue named, to trouble, moleſt, or diſquiet the Prieſts in the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the diuine ſeruice, or of the enioying and reaping of their tenths, fruits, and reuenues of their benefices, and all other rights and duties belonging
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4143:6"/> vnto them: and that all thoſe which in the time of the troubles haue bene taken away, as Churches, houſes, goods, or reuenues, belonging to the ſaid Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons, and that thoſe which do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and occupie the ſame, do ſurrender the whole poſſeſſion and peaceable fruition in ſuch rights, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and aſſurances as they had them before that they were diſſeized of the ſame. In moſt plaine tearmes alſo forbidding thoſe of the ſaid preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded reformed Religion, to make any Sermons, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exerciſe of their ſaid Religion in the Churches, houſes, and habitations of the ſaid Eccleſiaſticall perſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IIII.</head>
               <p>It ſhall be in the choyce of the ſayd Eccleſiaſtical perſons, to buy the houſes and buildings erected in places prophaned by them which occupied them during the time of the troubles, or elſe to conſtraine the poſſeſſers &amp; owners of the ſaid buildings to buy the grounds, &amp; in both caſes eſtimation to be made by ſuch as are wiſe and skilfull therin: in ſuch ſort, as that the parties may agree and conclude together: &amp; if they cannot be brought to agreement amongſt themſelues, then the Iudges of thoſe places ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the whole matter; the owners their aide and helpe alwayes reſerued vnto them, againſt ſuch as it may concerne or belong vnto. And in caſe where the ſaid Eccleſiaſticall perſons ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell thoſe in poſſeſſion to buy the ground, they (the ſaid Eccleſiaſticall perſons) ſhall not receiue the price of the valuation, but it ſhall remaine in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4143:6"/> hands of the poſſeſſed, and they ſtill ſtand anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the ſame, and for the profite for the ſame, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the rate of a pennie in twenty, vntill ſuch time as the ſame ſhall be imployed for the profite of the Church: and this likewiſe to be procured within the ſpace of a yeare. And if it happen that the ſame time be expired, and the money not imployed, and that the occupier of the ſame will not keepe it any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at the ſaid rent, he ſhall be diſcharged thereof in paying the ſame ouer to anie man that is able to pay the principall and the rent, hauing authority from a Iuſtice, and warrant for that which he ſhall do therein. And as concerning the holy places, there ſhall order be taken for them, by the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which ſhal be by vs ordained and appointed for the executing of this preſent Edict, hauing bene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by vs inſtructed what to do in this point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>And yet notwithſtanding the grounds and places occupied and imploied about the repairing and fortifying of the townes and other places of our Realme, as alſo the matter imploied that way, ſhall not be to be chalenged or redemanded by ſuch Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons, or elſe any other either pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique or priuate, except at ſuch times as the ſayd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations and fortifications ſhall be pulled downe by our appointment and ordinance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>And to the end that there may not be left any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of iarre or trouble amongſt our ſubiects, we haue permitted and doe permit thoſe of the ſayd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4143:7"/> pretended reformed religion, to liue and dwell in all the townes and places of this our Realme, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries vnder our iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without any maner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, vexatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, moleſtation, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pulſion to the doing of any thing in the matter of religion, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to their conſcience, &amp; not to be ſearched or ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſackt, in the houſes and places where they mind to abide and dwell, ſo that they carrie themſelues in all other their demeanour according to that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this our preſent Edict.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>We haue likewiſe licenſed al Lords, Gentlemen, and other perſons aſwel inhabiting this our Realme as others making profeſſion of the ſayd pretended reformed Religion, hauing in our kingdome and countries vnder our iuriſdiction, the priueledge of a Iuſtice of life and death, or a fee in Knights ſeruice (as in <hi>Normandy</hi>) whether he hold it as proprietarie thereunto, or as one hauing right and intereſt vnto the reuenewes of the ſame, in the whole, or in the halfe, or by the thirds, to haue in ſuch their houſes of Iuſtice of life and death, or in their ſee of Knights ſeruice (which yet they ſhall giue the names &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of vnto our Bailifes &amp; Lieutenants, euery one in his place of their principall dwelling houſe) the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the ſayd Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both whiles they are there reſident themſelues, as alſo their wiues or family, or any part thereof when they are abſent. And in caſe the title of this their tenure bearing to ſit as Iudges vpon life and death, or the title of a whole Knights ſee, be called in queſtion, and ſtand in controuerſie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4143:7"/> in the law, notwithſtanding the exerciſe of the ſayd Religion may be there kept; prouided that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties aforeſayd be actually poſſeſſed of the ſaid houſe, bearing ſuch commiſſion of ſitting as Iudge in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of life and death, although our Atturney gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall be a party therein. We further alſo permit and allow them, to haue the ſayd exerciſe in their other houſes priuiledged with the authority of ſitting as Iudge in matters of life &amp; death, or being a Knights fee, for the time they ſhall be reſident thereupon themſelues, and not otherwiſe: and all this to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood &amp; conſtrued in the behalfe of themſelues, their familie, ſubiects, and whatſoeuer others that will reſort thereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>In the houſes of thoſe which haue a ſee, where they of the ſayd Religion haue not the priuiledge of high Iuſtice, or of a Knights fee, they may not haue the ſayd exerciſe but for themſelues onely and their family. We meane not notwithſtanding that if there come in other perſons to the number of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty beſides their owne family, whether it be vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Baptiſme, the viſiting of their friends or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, that then they may be ſearched: except on the other ſide, that the ſaid houſes be in the townes, boroughs, or villages belonging to the Lords Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques high Iuſtices, &amp; thoſe, others then our ſelf: and wherein the ſayd Lords Catholikes haue their places: for in ſuch caſe thoſe of the ſayd Religion may not in the ſayd townes, boroughs, or villages exerciſe the ſame, except it be with the good leaue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4143:8"/> and licenſe of the ſayd Lords high Iuſtices, and not otherwiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>We permit likewiſe thoſe of the ſayd Religion, to hold and continue their exerciſes, in all the Townes and places within our iuriſdiction, where it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed and exerciſed by them publiquely &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and diuerſe times in the yeares 1596. and 1597. vnto the end of the moneth of Auguſt, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any Iudgement or ſentence contrarie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>In like manner the ſayd exerciſe may be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and reeſtabliſhed, in all the Townes and places where it hath bene eſtabliſhed, or ought to be by the Edict of Pacification made in the yeare 77. or by the particular articles, and conferences held at <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rac</hi> and <hi>Flex:</hi> without any impeachment vnto the ſaid eſtabliſhment in the places of <hi>Demaine,</hi> granted by the ſayd Edict, Articles and Conferences, for the places of Bayliwickes, or which ſhall ſo be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, notwithſtanding that they haue bene ſince then aliened and ſold away to Catholikes, or ſhal ſo be in time to come. And yet our meaning is not, that the ſaid exerciſe may be eſtabliſhed againe in the places of the ſaid <hi>Demaine,</hi> which haue bene heretofore poſſeſſed by them of the ſaid pretended reformed religion, where it hath bene planted only in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſafetie of their perſons, or becauſe of the priuiledge of the Lordſhips, if the ſaid Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips be found at this preſent to be in the poſſeſſion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4143:8"/> of ſuch perſons as are of the ſaid Catholike Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Romiſh Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>Furthermore in euery of the auncient Bayli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wikes, Lieutenantſhips, and gouernements ſtanding in ſtead of a bayliwike, &amp; being to haue chiefe and principall places in the Courts of Parliament, we ordaine, that in the Suburbes of ſome one Towne beſides thoſe which haue bene granted vnto them by the ſaid Edict, particular Articles and Conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and where there is no ſuch Townes, in ſome one borough or village, the exerciſe of the ſayd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reformed Religion may be publikly vſed for all ſuch as will go thereunto, notwithſtanding there be in the ſayd Bayliwiks, Lieutenantſhips, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernements, many places where the ſayd exerciſe is already eſtabliſhed: excepted from hence the ſayd place of Bayliwike newly agreed vpon by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Edict, and the Townes wherein there lyeth any Archbiſhop or Biſhop: and that without any thing letting, but that thoſe of the pretended reformed Religion, may demand &amp; name for the ſayd place of their ſayd exerciſe the boroughes &amp; villages neare vnto the ſayd Townes: excepted alſo the places and Seignories belonging to the ſayd Eccleſiaſtical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as wherein we doe not meane that the ſayd ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place of Bailiwike may be eſtabliſhed, hauing excepted and reſerued the ſame of our ſpecial grace and fauour. It is our pleaſure and meaning, that by the name of auncient Bayliwikes bee vnderſtood thoſe which were in the time of the deceaſed King
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4143:9"/> 
                  <hi>Henry</hi> our moſt Honourable Lord &amp; Father in law, held and taken for Bayliwikes, Lieutenantſhips, &amp; gouernements of chiefe and principall place in our ſayd Courts of Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>It is not our meaning by this preſent Edict, to derogate or take away any thing from the Edicts &amp; Agreements made heretofore, for the reducing of certaine Princes, Lords, Gentlemen, and Catholike Townes vnder our iuriſdiction, in that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the exerciſe of the ſayd Religion: which E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts and Agreements ſhall be maintained and kept in this reſpect, according as it ſhall be declared by the inſtructions giuen the Commiſſioners which ſhall be appointed for the execution of the preſent Edict.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>We expreſly forbid all them of the ſaid Religion, to vſe any exrciſe of the ſame, either by way of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, Gouernment, Diſcipline, or publike inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of children or others, in this our Realme and countries vnder our allegiance, in any thing concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except in the places permitted &amp; gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by this preſent Edict.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>XIIII.</head>
               <p>As alſo to vſe any exerciſe of the ſayd Religion in our Court &amp; traine, neither likewiſe in our lands &amp; countries beyond the mountaines, neither yet in our Citie of <hi>Paris,</hi> or within fiue leagues of the ſayd City: notwithſtanding thoſe of the ſayd Religion, dwelling in the ſayd coaſtes and countries beyond
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4143:9"/> the mountaines, and in our ſayd City, and within the compaſſe of fiue leagues round about the ſame, ſhal not be ſearched in their houſes, nor forced to the doing of any thing in the matter of Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their conſcience: ſo that they demeane the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in other things according as is enioyned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this our preſent Edict.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>In like manner the publike exerciſe of the ſayd Religion may not be vſed in warres, except in thoſe quarters whoſe Chiefetaines are profeſſors of the ſayd Religion, and yet furthermore it is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that thoſe quarters muſt be others then that in which we ſhall lodge in our owne proper perſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p>Following the ſecond Article of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference of <hi>Nerac,</hi> we permit them of the ſaid Religion, to build places for the exerciſe of the ſame, in the Cities and places where liberty and licenſe is graunted vnto them for the ſame: and further, ſuch places as they haue heretofore to that ende builded, ſhall be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto them, or elſe the grounds whereupon they ſtood, in ſuch ſtate as it now ſtandeth: Yea though they be in ſuch places as they may not be ſuffered to vſe the exerciſe of their Religion except they be tranſlated and changed into the nature of other buildings. In which caſe the poſſeſſors of the ſayd buildings, ſhall giue vnto them roomes and places of the ſame price and value that they were of before they were in that manner by them tranſlated, or the iuſt valuation of them in money at a rate ſet downe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4143:10"/> by ſuch as are skilfull. Reſerued alwayes vnto ſuch proprietaries and owners, whatſoeuer aide or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor which the law may any way offord them againſt any whom the matter may concerne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>We forbid all Preachers, Readers, and all others which vſe to ſpeake in the places of publike aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, to vſe any words, diſcourſes, or argument ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſtirring vp of the people vnto ſedition: hauing rather inioyned them, we do againe inioyne them, to carrie and behaue themſelues modeſtly, not vttering or ſpeaking of any thing but what may tend to the edification and inſtruction of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and to the maintenance of the peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility by vs eſtabliſhed in this our ſayd Realme, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the paines and penalty ſet downe in the former Edicts. Giuing expreſſe charge and commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto our generall Atturnies and their ſubſtitutes, to giue informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to their office, againſt ſuch as ſhall oppoſe themſelues by contrary practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in this point, vpon paine themſelues to anſwere in their owne perſons, and of depriuation from their offices, for fayling therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <p>We forbid in like manner all our Subiects, of what condition or quality ſoeuer they be, to traine or draw by force or ſecret and ſubtile ſuggeſtions, the children of the ſayd Religion, to cauſe them to be Baptized or confirmed in the Catholike Apoſtilike Romaine Church, contrary to the good liking of their parents. As likewiſe the ſame inhibitions are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4143:10"/> to be extended to them of the ſayd pretended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion: and that a like to both, vpon paine of being puniſhed for examples vnto all others, that they may beware to do the like.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <p>Thoſe of the pretended reformed Religion, ſhall not be any way tyed, or ſtand bound by reaſon of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurations, promiſes &amp; oathes which they haue made heretofore, or for any ſuretiſhip which they haue entred into in reſpect of the matter of the ſayd Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, neither ſhall they be moleſted or troubled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny manner of way at all for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <p>They ſhall in like manner be inioyned to keepe and obſerue the Feſtiuall dayes, appointed in the Catholike, Apoſtolike, Romaine Church, neither may they vpon thoſe dayes worke, ſell, or ſhew wares in their ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhops, neither likewiſe may handicrafts men worke out of their ſhops, either in chambers, or in their houſes ſhut cloſe to them, vpon the ſayd Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiuall dayes or any other prohibited, in any occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation or craft, which may make a noiſe to be heard without by ſuch as paſſe by, or yet of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. In which caſe alſo there ſhall not any ſearch be made but by ſuch as are appointed officers for the executing of Iuſtice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <p>The bookes concerning the pretended reformed Religion, may not be printed and ſold publikely, but in the Cities and places where the publike exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the ſayd Religion is permitted. And as for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4143:11"/> bookes which ſhall be printed in other Cities, they ſhall be ſeene and peruſed aſwell by our officers as Diuines, as is appointed by our decrees and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. We expreſly forbid the printing, publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and ſelling of all bookes, ſcrolles, or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, defamatory, and tending to the taking away of any mans good name, vpon the paines and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment contained in our decrees and ordenances: inioyning and charging all our Iudges and officers to be diligent in the executing of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <p>We furthermore ordaine, that there ſhall not be made any diſtinction or difference (in reſpect of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) in the receiuing of Scholers to be inſtructed &amp; trained vp in Vniuerſities, Colledges, or ſchooles, or of the ſicke and poore, in receiuing of them into Hoſpitals, houſes for the diſeaſed, or publike almes houſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <p>Thoſe of the pretended reformed Religion, ſhall be bound to keepe the lawes of the Catholike, Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolike, Romaine Church, receiued in this our Realme, concerning the matter of mariages already contracted or to be contracted, as alſo concerning the degrees of conſanguinity and affinity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <head>XXIIII.</head>
               <p>In like maner thoſe of the ſaid religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal pay the duties of entring, as it is accuſtomed for the charges and offices which ſhall be diſcharged for them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being conſtrained to giue their atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance about the executing of any ceremonies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie vnto their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4143:11"/> ſaid religion: and being vrged to an oath, they ſhall not be bound to make any other, then to hold vp their hand, and to ſweare and promiſe to God, that they will ſpeake the truth: and againe, they ſhall not be bound to take anie diſpenſation for oathes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by them in matters of bargaines, and obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <p>We wil and ordaine, that all thoſe of the ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reformed religion, and others which haue taken partie with that ſide, of what eſtate, qualitie, or condition ſoeuer they be, be bound and tied by all good and reaſonable wayes, and vpon paine of ſuch puniſhment as is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in the Edicts made for that purpoſe, to pay and diſcharge the tenths to the Curats and other Eccleſiaſticall perſons, and to all others to whom they belong and appertaine, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the vſe and cuſtome receiued in the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their abode.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <head>XXVI.</head>
               <p>Diſinheritings or depriuations, whether in ſtate of life, or in matters diſpoſed of by wil and teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, comming onely of hatred, or for the cauſe of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall not take place either for the time paſt, or that is to come amongſt our ſubiects.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <head>XXVII.</head>
               <p>To the end that the affections of our Subiects may be ſo much the better and more firmely knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as our purpoſe is, and to take away all diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments that may enſue: We declare all them which do or hereafter ſhall make profeſſion of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4143:12"/> ſaid pretended reformed religion, capable of hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and exerciſing all maner of Eſtates, dignities, offices, &amp; publike charges whatſoeuer, be they roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, Seigniories, or of the cities of our ſaid realme, countries, lands, and dominions vnder our allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, notwithſtanding all ſuch oaths as haue paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the contrary, and to be indifferently admitted and receiued there into. And as for our Courts of Parliament and other Iudges, it ſhall be ſufficient for them to informe &amp; enquire of the liues, maners, religion and honeſt conuerſation of them which are or ſhall be inueſted with offices, as well of the one religion, as of the other, without taking of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other oath, then of wel &amp; faithfully ſeruing the king, in the executing of their charges, and keeping of his ordinances, as hath from all time bene obſerued &amp; vſed. And when anie vacation falleth out of anie the ſaid Eſtates, charges, and offices, as for ſuch as ſhall be in our gift and diſpoſing, it ſhall therein be held indifferent for vs to appoint thereunto anie maner of perſons, as capable thereof without diſtinction, as being a thing ſo greatly making for the firmer vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our ſubiects. We mean likewiſe that thoſe of the ſaid prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded reformed religion may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and receiued into all maner of counſels, conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, deliberations, aſſemblies &amp; functions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the things aforeſaid, it being no barre or preiudice vnto them, to keepe them for enioying of the ſame, becauſe they are of the ſayd religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>XXVIII.</head>
               <p>We ordaine for the burying of the deceaſed of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4143:12"/> thoſe of the ſaid religion, that there ſhal ſpeedy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion be made through all the cities and places of this realme, and in euerie place thereof by our Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Magiſtrates, or elſe by thoſe Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which we ſhall depute for the execution of the preſent Edict, of ſome one place or other, in ſuch conuenient ſort and maner as poſſiblie may be. And ſuch Churchyards as they had heretofore, and are now depriued of, ſhal againe be reſtored vnto them, except it fall out, that at this preſent they be furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with buildings, of what quality ſoeuer, &amp; then in ſuch caſe there ſhall others be prouided for them freely without any their coſts or charges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>XXIX.</head>
               <p>We inioyne and ſtraightly giue in charge vnto our ſaid Officers, that ſuch diligence and endeuour be vſed in the ſaid matter of burying places, as that through their neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce there may not any ſcandale ariſe to any. And to come more particularly &amp; near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the point, be it knowne to ſuch Officers, that it ſhall be their parts, within fifteene dayes after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt made, to prouide for them of the ſaid religion a conuenient place for burials, without any further detracting of time or making of any delay, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paine of looſing fiue hundred Crownes, to be recouerd of their proper and priuate perſons. It is likewiſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden the ſaid Officers, and all others to exact or demaund any thing for the conducting &amp; bringing of the ſaid dead bodies vnto the ſaid places, vpon paine of being condemned as extortioners.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:4143:13"/>
               <head>XXX.</head>
               <p>And to the end that iuſtice may be adminiſtred vnto our ſubiects, without anie ſuſpition of hatred or fauour (it being one of the principall meanes for the nouriſhing of peace and concord) we haue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and do ordaine, that in our Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Paris, there ſhall be eſtabliſhed one Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber or Court, conſiſting of a Preſident and ſixteene Counſellers of the ſaid Parliament, which ſhall be called by the name and title of the Edict-court or Chamber, and they ſhall be not only to deale in the cauſes and ſutes of thoſe of the ſaid prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med religion, which ſhall be within the ordinarie reach of the ſaid Court, but alſo with the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of our Parliaments of <hi>Normandy</hi> &amp; <hi>Brittaine,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the authoritie which ſhall hereafter be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed and granted vnto the ſame by the preſent Edict: and this to be continued vntill in euerie of the ſaid Parliaments there be eſtabliſhed a Court for the doing of iuſtice in the places ſuing therunto. We further ordaine, that of the foure Offices of Counſellours in our ſaid Parliament of Paris, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and eſtabliſhed according to the forme &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the laſt inſtitution and appointment made by vs, there be preſently prouided &amp; receiued into the ſaid Parliament foure of them of the ſaid pretended reformed religion, ſuch as are ſufficient and capable of the ſame, and that they be beſtowed or placed, the chiefe and principall in the ſaid Court of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, and the other three according to the meaſure of gifts graunted them into the three Courts of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4143:13"/> Inquirie: &amp; further that for the two firſt offices of lay Counſellers of the ſayd Court that ſhal fall void by death, there ſhall likewiſe be prouided two of the ſaid prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded reformed religion, and the ſame taken in and placed: the like courſe ſhall be taken in the two other Courts of Inquirie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <head>XXXI.</head>
               <p>Beſides the Court heretofore eſtabliſhed at <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres,</hi> for the precincts and liberties of our Court of Parliament at <hi>Tholoſa,</hi> and which ſhall be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the eſtate it ſtandeth, we haue for the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations ordained, and do ordaine, that in euery one of the Courts of Parliament of <hi>Grenoble</hi> &amp; <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux,</hi> there ſhall be likewiſe eſtabliſhed a Court, conſiſting of two Preſidents, the one a Catholike, and the other of the pretended reformed religion, and of twelue Counſellers, ſixe wherof ſhall be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, and the other ſixe of the ſaid religion: the which Preſident and Counſellers Catholikes ſhall be by vs taken and choſen out of the bodies of our ſaid Courts: and as for them of the ſaid religion, there ſhall a new creation be made of one Preſident and ſix Counſellers for the Parliament of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> and of one. Preſident and three Counſellers for the Parliament of <hi>Grenoble</hi> which with the three Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers of the ſaid religion, which are already in the ſaid Parliament, ſhall be imployed in the ſaid Court of <hi>Dolphinie.</hi> And the ſaid Offices ſhall be created with a new creation, hauing allowed them the ſame fees, honours, authorities and preheminences that others of the ſayd Courts haue. And the ſyad
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4143:14"/> ſeat of the ſayd Court of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> ſhalbe in the ſayd citie of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> or at <hi>Nerac,</hi> and that of <hi>Dolphine</hi> and <hi>Grenoble.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <head>XXXII.</head>
               <p>The ſayd Court of <hi>Dolphine</hi> ſhall determine the cauſes of thoſe of the ſaid pretended reformed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, being within the products and liberties of our Parlament of <hi>Prouence,</hi> without hauing need to ſue out any writs for the remouing of the cauſes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet anie other letters of confirmation, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as are to be had in our court of Chauncerie in <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phine:</hi> as alſo thoſe of the ſaid religion of <hi>Normandy</hi> and <hi>Brittaine,</hi> ſhal not be bound to ſue out any writs of remouing of cauſes, neither yet other letters of confirmation, then thoſe which are to be had in our court of Chauncerie at <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <head>XXXIII.</head>
               <p>Our ſubiects of the ſaid religion of the Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> ſhall haue their choice to haue their matters pleaded and heard either in the court or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> or in that of <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phine.</hi> And accordingly ſhall be acquited and freed from ſuing out their writs of remoue and letters of confirmation from any where elſe, then in the ſaid courts of Chancerie of <hi>Paris</hi> or <hi>Dolphine,</hi> according as they themſelues ſhall thinke good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>XXXIIII.</head>
               <p>All the ſaid Courts compoſed and appointed as aforeſaid, ſhal determine and iudge with ſoueraigne authoritie and vnauoydable ſentence, by iudgement vncontrolleable by anie others of the ſutes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies raiſed or to be raiſed, in which thoſe of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4143:14"/> ſaid pretended reformed religion ſhal be the parties principal, or the warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding or defending: &amp; that in all maner of matters, either ciuill or crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, whether the ſaid ſute be by writ or extemporal appeale, and that if it ſo ſeeme good to the ſaid par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the one of them require the ſame before proteſtation made in the cauſe, in regard of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing of the ſute: excepted notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding al mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of benefices, the perſonages not impropriate, eccleſiaſticall patronages, and all other ſuch cauſes as wherein ſhall be handled the rights and duties or reuenues of the Church, all which ſhall be handled and iudged by the courts of Parliament, the ſaid Aſſemblies and courts of the Edict hauing nothing to do to take acknowledgment of the ſame. As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is our will and pleaſure, that for the iudging and deciding of cauſes criminall, which ſhal happen betwixt the ſaid Eccleſiaſticall perſons, and thoſe of the ſaid pretended reformed religion, if the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall partie be defendant, in ſuch caſe the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and iudgement of ſuch cauſes criminall ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto our ſoueraigne &amp; high Courts, denying all dealing therin vnto the ſaid courts of the Edicts: and where ſuch Eccleſiaſticall partie ſhall be plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tife, and the partie of the ſaid religion defendant, the triall and iudgement of ſuch criminall cauſe ſhal appertaine by appeale, and with power of abſolute &amp; definitiue ſentence to be determined of, in the ſaid eſtabliſhed Courts of the Edict. The ſaid courts likewiſe ſhall heare and examine in vacation times ſuch matters as by the Edicts and ordinances are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4143:15"/> &amp; apointed to be heard and examined of the ſaid eſtabliſhed courts in vacation times, euerie one in his precinct and iuriſdiction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <head>XXXV.</head>
               <p>The ſaid court of <hi>Grenoble</hi> from henceforth ſhal be vnited and incorporated to the body of the ſaid court of Parliament, and the Counſellers and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of the ſaid pretended reformed religion, called Preſidents and Counſellers of the ſaid court, and ſo held and accounted of the ranke &amp; number of the ſame: and for theſe purpoſes they ſhall be firſt diſpoſed of &amp; placed in the other Courts, and after drawne out from them to be imployed and do their ſeruice in ſuch courts as we ſhall ordaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new: and withall in the places of their charge where they ſhall be aſſiſtant, they ſhall haue a voice and ſeat in all the conſultations which ſhall be held by the officers of the courts aſſembled and come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſhall enioy the ſame fees, authoritie and preheminences with the other Preſidents and Counſellours of the ſaid court.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <head>XXXVI.</head>
               <p>And further it is our wil and intent, that the ſaid Courts of <hi>Castres</hi> and <hi>Burdeaux</hi> be reunited and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated in the ſayd Parliaments, after the ſame manner that the others are, when neede ſhall be; and that the cauſes mouing vs to make ſuch eſtabliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhall ceaſe, and ſhall not haue any more place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſubiects: and for the ſame purpoſes the Preſidents and Counſellors of them of the ſayd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4143:15"/> ſhall be called and held for Preſidents and Counſellours of the ſayd Courts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <head>XXXVII.</head>
               <p>There ſhall be likewiſe created and ordained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new in the Court ordained for the Parliament of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> two Subſtitutes of our Atturney and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate generall, of which our Atturney ſhall be a Catholike, and the other of the ſayd Religion; and theſe ſhall be inueſted with the ſayd offices &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent fees allowed thereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <head>XXXVIII.</head>
               <p>The two ſayd Subſtitutes ſhall not take vppon them any other quality or condition, but that of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes, and when the Courts ordained for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments of <hi>Tholoſa</hi> and <hi>Burdeaux</hi> ſhall be vnited &amp; incorporated vnto the ſayd Parliaments, the ſayd Subſtitutes ſhall be placed in the offices of Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours in the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <head>XXXIX.</head>
               <p>The diſpatch of writs out of the Chauncery of the Court of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> ſhall be in the preſence of two of the Counſellers of the ſayd Court, whereof the one ſhall be a Catholike, and the other of the ſayd pretended reformed Religion: in their abſence one of the Maiſters of the Requeſts of our ſayd Towne Houſe, and one of the <hi>Notaries</hi> Secretaries of the ſayd Court of Parliament of <hi>Bordeaux</hi> ſhall keepe reſidence in the place where the ſayd Court ſhall be eſtabliſhed, or elſe one of the Secretaries Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Chauncery to ſigne the writs of the ſayd Chauncery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:4143:16"/>
               <head>XL.</head>
               <p>We will and ordaine, that in the ſayd Court of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> there ſhall be two choſen out and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Regiſters of the ſayd Parliament, the one in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and the other in Criminall cauſes, which ſhall exerciſe the ſayd charges by vertue of our Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, &amp; ſhall be called Commiſſioners for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter Court Ciuill and Criminall, and therefore ſhall not at any time be caſt out or diſanulled by the ſayd Regiſters of the Parliament: &amp; yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they ſhall be bound to render the profite and commodity of the ſayd Regiſter Court vnto the ſayd Regiſters or Clarkes. Which ſayd Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhall be rewarded by the ſayd Regiſters as ſhal be adiudged and thought meete by the ſayd Court. Furthermore there ſhall be ordained Sergeants that are Catholikes, which ſhall bee taken in the ſayd Court, or from elſewhere, according as we ſhall thinke it beſt: beſides which, there ſhall alſo be two of the ſaid religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> newly ordained &amp; freely prouided for, &amp; al the ſayd Sergeants ſhall be ruled by the ſaid Court, aſwell in the diſcharging and deuiding of their charge and buſineſſe, as of the profits &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities which they ought to take. There ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be giuen forth Commiſſion for a Payer of fees, and for a Receiuer or Collector of the fines and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercements of the ſayd Court, for to haue ſuch a one prouided as we ſhall thinke good, if the Court be kept any where elſe then in the ſayd City. And the Commiſſion heretofore graunted vnto the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter of the fees for the Court of <hi>Caſtres,</hi> ſhal take
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4143:16"/> his full and intire effect: and there ſhall be ioyned vnto the ſayd charge, the Commiſſion of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts of the fines and amercements of the ſayd Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="part">
               <head>XLI.</head>
               <p>There ſhall care be had for the good and ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of fees for the officers of the Courts or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by this Edict.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <head>XLII.</head>
               <p>The Preſidents, Counſellers and other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like officers of the ſayd Courts, ſhall be continued as long as poſſibly may be, and as we ſhall ſee it to make for our ſeruice &amp; the good of our ſubiects, &amp; in this time of thus bearing with and tollerating of the one, there ſhall prouiſion be made of others to ſucceed them in their places, before their departure, and therewithall in ſuch ſort, as that during the time of ſuch their ſeruice, it ſhall not be lawfull for them to depart or be abſent from the ſayd Courts without leaue granted, by them which ſhall be Iudges in the cauſes concerning the Ordenance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <head>XLIII.</head>
               <p>The ſayd Courts ſhall be eſtabliſhed within ſixe monethes, during the which time (if the eſtabliſhing therof do ſtay ſo long before it be brought to paſſe) the ſutes riſen or to riſe, in which thoſe of the ſayd religion ſhall be parties, and of the iuriſdiction and within the precincts of our Parliaments of <hi>Paris, Roane, Dion</hi> or <hi>Renes,</hi> ſhall bee remoued into the Court already eſtabliſhed at <hi>Paris,</hi> by vertue of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4143:17"/> Edict made in the yeare 1577. or elſe into the great Counſell, at the choiſe and liberty of thoſe of the ſayd religion, as they themſelues ſhal require. Thoſe which ſhall be of the Parliament of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> in the Court eſtabliſhed at <hi>Caſtres,</hi> or in the ſayd great Counſell, as they themſelues ſhall thinke good: &amp; thoſe which ſhall be of Prouence in the Parliament of <hi>Grenoble</hi> And if the ſayd Courts be not eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed within three monethes after the preſentation and ſetting forth of this our preſent Edict, then ſuch of our Parliaments as ſhall haue refuſed, ſhall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to examine and iudge of the cauſes of thoſe of the ſayd religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="part">
               <head>XLIIII.</head>
               <p>Sutes not yet iudged but depending in the ſayd Courts of Parliament and great Counſell of the quality aforeſaid, ſhal be remoued, in what eſtate ſo euer they ſtand in the ſayd Courts, euery one to the Court within the iuriſdiction and liberties wherein they dwell (if either of the parties of the ſayd religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do ſo require) within foure monethes after the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment of the ſame: and as for thoſe which ſhalbe diſcontinued and are not in eſtate to iudge (the ſayd of the religion ſhall be enioyned to make declaration vpon the firſt notice and ſignification which ſhall be giuen them of the action in law, and the ſayd time paſt,) they ſhall not afterward be any more admitted to make their ſayd appeales or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="part">
               <head>XLV.</head>
               <p>The ſayd Courts of <hi>Grenoble</hi> and <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> as alſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4143:17"/> that of <hi>Caſtres</hi> ſhall keepe the formes and ſtyles of thoſe Parliaments within whoſe precincts they are held, and ſhall ſit in equall number of the one and of the other religion to iudge, if the parties amongſt themſelues agree not to the contrary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="part">
               <head>XLVI.</head>
               <p>All Iudges to whom directions and order ſhall be giuen, for the executions of definitiue ſentences and finall iudgements, Commiſſions of the ſayd Courts and letters obtained in the Chaunceries of the ſame, as alſo all Sergeants ſhall be bound to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the ſame, and the ſayd Sergeants to doe all their buſineſſe and matters of execution through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our Realme without demanding any <hi>Placet, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ne pareatis,</hi> vpon paine of ſuſpenſion from their eſtates, and of the charges, damages, and coſts of the parties, the determination of which point ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine vnto the ſayd Courts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="part">
               <head>XLVII.</head>
               <p>There ſhall not any appeales be granted for any cauſes, the determining whereof belongeth to the ſayd Courts, except in matters concerning the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances: and then ſuch appeale and remoue ſhalbe to the neareſt court eſtabliſhed, following our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, and the deuiding of the ſuits of the ſaid courts ſhal be iudged of in the next adioyning, the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and forme of the ſaid Courts obſerued, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſuits ſhall be commenced and layd: the court of the Edict in our Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> excepted, where the ſuits deuided ſhal be deuided in the ſame court by the Iudges which ſhall be by vs named by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4143:18"/> our particular letters directed to that end, if the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties do not rather deſire to ſtay the renewing of the ſayd Court. And if it happen that one and the ſame ſute be deuided into all the Courts halfe deuided, the deuiding ſhall be remoued to the ſaid Court of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="part">
               <head>XLVIII.</head>
               <p>The appeales which ſhall bee made from any Preſidents and Counſellers of Courts halfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, ſhall be iudged by the number of ſixe, to the which number the parties ſhall be bound to referre themſelues, for otherwiſe it ſhall proceede, any manner of appeales to the contrary notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="part">
               <head>XLIX.</head>
               <p>The triall of Preſidents and Counſellers newly elected and made in the ſayd Courts halfe deuided, ſhall be made in our Priuie Counſell, or by the ſayd Courts euery one in his place, when they ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t number: &amp; notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the oath accuſtomed, ſhall be by them taken in the Courts, where the ſayd Courts ſhall bee held: and if refuſe thereof be made, then in our Priuy Counſell; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe of the Court of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> which ſhall take their oath at the hands of our Chaunceller, or in the ſame Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="part">
               <head>L.</head>
               <p>We will and ordaine, that the receiuing and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our officers of the ſayd religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be iudged and determined in our Courts halfe deuided by the greater number of voices: as it is accuſtomed to be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4143:18"/> done in other iudgements; ſo that there ſhall not be any need that the affirmatiue voices, or approuing iudgements be more then two thirds, following the Ordenance, which for that cauſe we will to be abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="part">
               <head>LI.</head>
               <p>There ſhall bee made, handled, and contriued in the ſayd Courts halfe deuided, ſuch queſtions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations and reſolutions, as ſhall appertaine to the publike peace and quietneſſe, and as may concerne the particular eſtate and ciuill gouernment of ſuch cities as the ſayd Courts are held and kept in.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="part">
               <head>LII.</head>
               <p>The Article of the iuriſdiction of the ſayd Courts, ordained by this preſent Edict, ſhall be followed &amp; obſerued, according to his forme and tenour: yea euen in that which doth concerne the executing, or not executing, or the breaking &amp; infringing of our Edicts, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they of the ſayd religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall be parties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="part">
               <head>LIII.</head>
               <p>The vnder officers Royall or others, whoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance belongeth vnto our Courts of Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, if they be of the ſayd pretended reformed religion, ſhall be examined and admitted in the ſayd Courts, that is to ſay, thoſe within the liberties of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Paris, Normandy,</hi> and <hi>Brittaine,</hi> in the ſayd Court of <hi>Paris;</hi> thoſe of <hi>Dolphinie</hi> and <hi>Prouence,</hi> in the Court of <hi>Grenoble:</hi> thoſe of <hi>Burgundy</hi> in the ſayd Court of <hi>Paris</hi> or <hi>Dolphinie,</hi> as they ſhall thinke beſt themſelues: Thoſe of the liberties of <hi>Tholoſa,</hi> in the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4143:19"/> Court of <hi>Castres:</hi> &amp; thoſe of the Parliament of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux</hi> in the Court of <hi>Guyenne,</hi> no oppoſitions, or parties making by others being to be vſed, beſides our Atturnies generall and their ſubſtitutes, and thoſe which are already ſetled in the ſayd offices: &amp; notwithſtanding the oath accuſtomed, ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by them in the Courts of Parliament, which ſhall haue nothing to do with their admittance, and in caſe of refuſing to take their oath in the ſayd Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, the ſayd officers ſhall take their oathes in the ſayd Courts, after the taking whereof they ſhall be charged to preſent by ſome Sergeant or Notary the act of their admittance to the Regiſters of the ſayd Court of Parliament, and with them to leaue a copie thereof conferred and examined with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall by the ſayd Regiſters, whoſe duty it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter the ſaid acts, vpon paine of paying all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties coſts and charges: and where the ſayd Regiſters ſhall refuſe to doe the ſame, it ſhall be ſufficient for the ſayd officers to bring backe the act of the ſayd breuiarie diſpatched and ſent away by the ſayd Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants or Notaries, &amp; to cauſe the ſame to be regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the Regiſters court of their ſaid iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, there to haue recourſe vnto the ſame, vpon paine of the diſanulling of their proceedings &amp; iudgements. And as concerning the officers, whereof there hath not bene accuſtomed any admittance to be made in our ſayd Courts of Parliament, in caſe that they to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it belonged did refuſe to proceed to the ſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination and admittance, then ſuch officers ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſhal withdraw themſelues from out of the ſaid
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4143:19"/> Courts, til ſuch order be taken for them as ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long thereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="part">
               <head>LIIII.</head>
               <p>The officers of the ſaid pretended reformed reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which ſhall hereafter be appointed to ſerue in the body of our ſayd courts of Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, great Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, court of Accompts, court of Aides, in the office of the Rolles, of the generall Treaſurers of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> or as other officers of the fines; ſhall be examined and admitted into the places where they were wont to be: and in caſe they be reiected and refuſed or iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice denied vnto them, then and in ſuch caſe they ſhalbe prouided for by our Priuie Counſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="part">
               <head>LV.</head>
               <p>The admitting of our Officers made in the court heretofore eſtabliſhed at <hi>Caſtres,</hi> ſhall continue and abide of force, notwithſtanding whatſoeuer ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, iudgements or ordinances paſſed to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. The admitting alſo of Iudges, Counſellers, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects, and other Officers of the ſaid religion made in our priuie Counſell, or by Commiſſioners by vs or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, for the refuſal made by our courts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, courts of Accounts, and courts of Aides, ſhall ſtand and continue in force, and that as full and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, as if they had bene made in the ſaid courts, by the other Iudges to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the admitta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, &amp; their fees ſhal be anſwered &amp; allowed by the court of Accompts, without any queſtion or doubt made of the ſame. And if any ſuch haue bene razed or croſſed out, they ſhall be reeſtabliſhed and put in againe, without further neede of hauing anie other
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4143:20"/> command then this preſent Edict, and without anie ſhewing of anie other admittance by the ſaid Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, notwithſtanding whatſoeuer iudgements paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the contrarie: for they ſhall be to no more end, then as if they had not bene, &amp; void of all force and effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="part">
               <head>LVI.</head>
               <p>And during the time that the fines and amerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the ſaid courts ſhall come ſhort of anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and defraying the coſts and charges of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of Iuſtice in the ſaid Courts, there ſhall be by vs appointed a ſufficient allowance for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the ſaid coſts, without any leauying of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch moneys vpon the goods of condemned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="part">
               <head>LVII.</head>
               <p>The Preſidents and Counſellers of the ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reformed religion before admitted into our court of Parliament of <hi>Dolphine,</hi> and into the court of the Edict incorporated into the ſame, ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue and enioy their places and degrees before en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed in the ſame, that is, the Preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as they haue enioyed them heretofore, and do at this day enioy them, and the Counſellers holding on according to the decrees and ratifications made them in our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie Counſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="part">
               <head>LVIII.</head>
               <p>We declare and pronounce, all ſentences, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, proceedings, ſeyſures, ſales &amp; decrees, made and graunted againſt them of the ſaid pretended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed religion, whether liuing or dead, ſince the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4143:20"/> deceaſe of the late deceaſed King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond our moſt honorable Lord and father in Law, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſaid religion, tumults and troubles ſince then befallen, as likewiſe the executions of thoſe iudgements &amp; decrees, from this day forward to be extinct, reuoked, &amp; diſanulled, &amp; the ſame do extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh or fruſtrate, reuoke and diſanull. We ordaine that they ſhal be razed &amp; taken from the Regiſters of the court of Regiſtry, as alſo out of whatſouer other courts, whether High and Great, or Inferiour and lower ones. As we will likewiſe that there be taken away and defaced, all the markes, notes and monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the ſaid executions, bookes, and diffama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie acts againſt their perſons, memorie, and poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and that the places wherein hath bene commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and performed any pulling downe, ruining, or razing for this occaſion, be reſtored in ſuch eſtate as they were, vnto the proprietaries and owners of the ſame, to hold, enioy, and diſpoſe of the ſame as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them. And generally, we haue fruſtrated, reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and diſanulled all proceedings and informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made againſt whatſoeuer enterpriſes, prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded crimes of high treaſon, and others, which procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and iudgements, containing reuniting, incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, and confiſcation notwithſtanding, we will that thoſe of the ſaid religion, and others their follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers and heires do reenter into the reall and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all poſſeſſion of all and euerie part of their goods.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="part">
               <head>LIX.</head>
               <p>All maner of proceedings paſt, and all definitiue ſentences and iudgements pronounced during the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4143:21"/> troubles againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſaid religion, which haue caried armes, or withdrawne themſelues out of our realme, or within the ſame, into the cities and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries by them held, and that for no other matter then for their religion and the troubles ſake: as likewiſe al maner of ſuits left off long ago, all preſcriptions, aſwell grounded vpon the law, as agreed vpon by couenants, or confirmed by cuſtome, and al ſeiſures made by the Lords vpon Manors or Lordſhips fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the time of the ſaid troubles, or through law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full impediments, cauſed through the ſame, as the iuſt examination thereof by our Iudges, ſhall better make to appeare, ſhall be accounted as not done, pronounced or come to paſſe: and we haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and do declare them for ſuch, and haue paſſed them ouer, and ſtill do paſſe them ouer for nothing, and that without leauing anie hope to the parties of euer releeuing themſelues in thoſe caſes, by any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meanes: and the rather, ſeeing it is our will and pleaſure that ſuch things ſhould be reſtored vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame eſtate, wherin they ſtood in former time (the ſaid iudgements &amp; executions of the ſame not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding) and ſuch poſſeſſion as they enioyed, againe giuen vnto them, and that for the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard and conſideration. And this ordinance ſhall furthermore in like maner take place, in reſpect of others which haue taken partie with them of the ſaid religion, or which haue bene abſent out of our realme becauſe of the troubles. And as concerning the children that were vnder age, of ſuch perſons as were of the aforeſayd quality, and died in the time
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4143:21"/> of the troubles, we reſtore them, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſayd chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren vnto the ſame eſtate and condition that they were in before time, without redeeming of the ſame, or being bound to disburſe any thing for any fines or amercements impoſed vpon the ſame. And yet we meane not, that the iudgements paſſed by the Iudges, Preſidents, or anie other the inferiour Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges againſt ſuch of the ſaid religion, or ſuch as haue followed that ſide, and taken parties with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould ſtand voyd, if they were paſſed by the ſayd ſitting in the townes poſſeſſed and held by them, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they might haue free acceſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="part">
               <head>LX.</head>
               <p>The Iudgements paſſed in our courts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in matters, the examination, hearing, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining whereof appertained to the Courts or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the Edict of the yeare 1577. and the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of <hi>Nerac</hi> and <hi>Flex,</hi> and in which courts the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties haue not willingly proceeded, that is to ſay, haue alleaged and propounded meanes of euaſion, and ſhifts to haue auoyded them, or elſe haue had them miniſtred directly vnto them, through default and want of appearance, as well in matters ciuil as criminall, notwithſtanding which ſhifts, the ſayd parties haue bene conſtrained to continue their courſe of triall: ſhall likewiſe bee made voyde and of no force. And in conſideration of iudgements paſſed againſt thoſe of the ſayd Religion, which haue proceeded willingly and without ſeeking how to be freed from the ſame, ſuch ſentences ſhal ſtand and abide: and yet neuertheleſſe without preiudice
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4143:22"/> of the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſame, they may (if they haue any mind thereunto) find reliefe by petition, ſuch as is vſed in ciuill cauſes before the courts ordained by this preſent Edict, ſo that the time limited by the ordinances be not too farre ſpent to their preiudice: and againe vntill ſuch time as the ſaid Courts and Chanceries of the ſame be eſtabliſhed, appeales made by word or writing, and entred by them of the ſaid religion before the Iudges, Regiſters, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners or executioners of the ſaid definitiue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and iudgements, ſhall haue like effect, as if they were relieued by the Princes letters patents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="part">
               <head>LXI.</head>
               <p>In all enquiries that ſhall be made, for what cauſe ſoeuer it be in matters ciuill, if the Inquiſitor or commiſſioner be a Catholike, the parties to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined ſhall know it to be their parts and dutie to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree vpon ſome one to ſtand aſſiſtant with him, and whereas they cannot agree, the ſaid commiſſioner or Inquiſitor ſhall take out of the office ſome one that ſhal be of the ſaid pretended reformed religion: and the ſame courſe ſhall be practiſed when the Commiſſioner or Inquiſitor ſhal be of the ſaid reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion for one to ſtand aſſiſtant with him, &amp; the ſame ſhall be a Catholike.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="part">
               <head>LXII.</head>
               <p>We wil and ordaine, that our Iudges may deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of the validity and efficacie of ſuch wils and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments as thoſe of the ſaid religion ſhall be inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted in, if they require the ſame, and the appeales from the ſaid iudgements ſhall be to be relieued in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4143:22"/> the ſayd courts, ordained for the ſutes of thoſe of the religion: any or all cuſtomes whatſouer contrarie hereunto notwithſtanding; no not that of <hi>Brittaine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="part">
               <head>LXIII.</head>
               <p>To meete with all the controuerſies that might happen amongſt our courts of parliament, &amp; thoſe courts belonging to the ſaid courts, and ordained by this our preſent Edict, there ſhal be by vs drawne and ſet downe a good and large direction and order betwixt court and court; and that ſuch a one, as that thoſe of the ſaid pretended reformed religion may wholly and throughly enioy the ſaid Edict: which order and direction ſhall be verified in our courts of parliament, and kept and obſerued without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing relation to the former going before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="part">
               <head>LXIIII.</head>
               <p>We forbid all our high courts and others of this realme, to iudge and determine the ciuill and crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſuits depending or falling betwixt thoſe of the ſaid religion, the determining and iudging wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by our Edict is confirmed vnto the ſaid courts of the Edict: prouided that the writ of remoue be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, as it is ſaid in the 40. Article aboue ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="part">
               <head>LXV.</head>
               <p>We will alſo (by the way of Prouiſo, and that ſo long as till we haue otherwiſe ordained) that in all ſutes raiſed or hereafter riſing, where they of the ſayd religion ſhal be in the ſtate and quality of plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifs or defendants, the parties, principals or authors in matters ciuill, wherein our officers and Preſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4143:23"/> ſeats haue power to iudge in moſt abſolute and peremptory manner, it may be permitted them, to require that two of the Court where their ſutes muſt be tried and iudged, doe abſtaine from ſitting in iudgement vpon, or medling with them; which two (without further cauſe expreſſed) ſhall know it to be their part and duty thereupon to abſtaine (any thing contained in the ordenance notwithſtanding) whereby the iudged ſhall of neceſſity become com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent and free from all deſert of refuſall, without iuſt cauſe: there being reſerued vnto them ſtill ouer and beſides this, ſuch refuſall and exceptions as are grounded vpon right and equity againſt the others: and in criminall matters wherein alſo the ſayd Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and others the Kings vnder Iudges do deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and iudge as afore in moſt abſolute and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory manner, thoſe that come before them (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſayd religion) may require, that three of the ſayd Iudges do leaue of to haue any thing to do with their cauſe, without further yeelding of reaſon for any ſuch their requeſt. And the Prouoſt-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> vnder Baylifes, vnder Stewards, Lieutenants of the ſhort robes, and other officers of like quality, ſhall giue iudgement following the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and directions heretofore deliuered, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard &amp; conſideration of the matter of vagabounds: and as for dwelling places ſurcharged and brought before them for matters concerning the Prouoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, if they bee of the ſayd religion, they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that three of the Iudges which haue power to ſit in Iudgement, would notwithſtanding ceaſe and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4143:23"/> abſtaine from dealing at all in their cauſes and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and that thereupon the ſayd three ſhall accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly take it their parts to giue ouer all dealing in the ſame, without further expectation of any cauſe or reaſon for the ſame: excepted alwayes if in the company where the ſayd cauſes ſhall bee iudged, there be to be found to the number of two in ciuill matters, and to the number of three in criminal cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the ſayd religion: for in ſuch caſe it ſhall not be permitted them to take vp any ſuch exceptions againſt any, without ſhewing of good and ſufficient reaſon: which courſe ſhall be common and recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally vſed by the Catholikes according to the forme and manner aboue ſpecified, in regard of the ſayd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall and exceptions taken againſt any of the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whereas thoſe of the ſayd pretended refo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ed religion ſhall be of the greater number. We do not meane notwithſtanding, that the ſayd Preſidentiall roomes of Prouoſt-Marſhals, vnder-Baylifs, vnder-Stewards, &amp; others which haue authority to iudge in abſolute &amp; peremptory maner, ſhold take by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that which hath bin ſaid the knowledge of the troubles paſt. And as for the crimes &amp; outrages co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vppon other occaſion then the troubles ſince the beginning of the moneth of March, from the yeare 1585. vnto the end of the yeare 1597. in caſe that they come to their hearing and determining, we will that therein they may make appeale to haue their cauſes brought before the Courts ordained by this preſent Edict. As it ſhall in like manner be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed for ſuch Catholikes as haue bene companions
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4143:24"/> in wickedneſſe, and where thoſe of the ſayd preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded reformed religion ſhall be parties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="part">
               <head>LXVI.</head>
               <p>We will likewiſe and ordaine, that from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth in all manner of inſtructions being of other quality then the informations of Criminall contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies in the Lieutena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries of <hi>Tholoſa, Carcaſſonne, Rouergue, Loragais, Beziers, Montpellier</hi> and <hi>Niſmes,</hi> the Magiſtrate or Commiſſioner deputed for the ſayd inſtructions, if he be a Catholike, ſhalbe bound to take vnto him one of the pretended reformed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion for an aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, being ſuch as the parties ſhalbe agreed vpon, and in caſe they cannot agree vpon any one, then there ſhall be taken out of the office one of the ſayd religion, by the foreſayd Magiſtrate or Commiſſioner: as in like caſe if the ſayd Magiſtrate or Commiſſioner bee of the ſayd Religion, he ſhall be bound in the ſame manner as is aforeſayd to take a Catholike aſſiſtant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="part">
               <head>LXVII.</head>
               <p>When there ſhal be called in queſtion any crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall controuerſie by the Prouoſts-Marſhals or their deputies, againſt any one of the ſayd religion that is ſetled in a dwelling place, as charging and accuſing him of ſome capital crime; the ſaid Prouoſts or their deputies, if they be Catholikes, ſhalbe bound to call to the hearing, examining, and determining of the inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or inditeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t framed to the matter, one aſſiſtant of the ſayd Religion: and the ſayd aſſiſtant ſhall ioyne with him in the iudgement of compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, and in the iudgement or ſentence definitiue
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4143:24"/> to be pronounced in the ſayd criminall cauſe: which competency or indifferency cannot be iudged but in the Preſidentiall roome or iuriſdiction next ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning, in an open aſſembly, with the principall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the ſayd ſeate, which ſhalbe found vpon the places, vpon paine of a nullity; except that ſuch as are come before them had made requeſt, that the competency might be iudged in the ſayd Court or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the preſent Edict. In which caſe of the dwelling houſes in the Prouinces of <hi>Guyenne, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc, Prouence,</hi> &amp; <hi>Dolphinie,</hi> the Subſtitutes of our Atturneyes generall in the ſaid courts ſhall cauſe (at the requeſt of ſuch as are there ſetled in houſes) to be brought into the ſame the charges &amp; informations put vp againſt them, that ſo they may know and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne whether the matters be capitall or no, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward according to the quality of the crimes they may be by the ſayd Courts referred to the ordinary, or to be iudged by the authority of the Prouoſts, as they ſhall ſee reaſon moſt to perſwade them to doe, obſeruing what is contained in our preſent Edict. And the Preſidentiall Iudges, Prouoſt-Marſhals, vnder-Balyfs, deputy Lieutenants and others which haue abſolute power definitiuely and peremptorily to iudge, ſhall be bound, reſpectiuely to obey and ſatisfy the iuriſdictions which ſhalbe inioyned them by the ſayd Courts: altogether in ſuch ſort as they haue accuſtomed to do vnto the ſayd Parliaments, vppon paine of being depriued of their eſtate and dignity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:4143:25"/>
               <head>LXVIII</head>
               <p>All Cries, Billes of ſale, and port-ſales of herita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, by which any man goeth about to proſecute the courſe of the law and directions of the Decree, ſhall be made in places and at houres accuſtomed, if it may poſſibly be ſo done, following the maner layd downe in our ordinances; or elſe in the publike mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, if ſo be in the places where ſuch heritages are ſituate and lying there be any market kept; but and if there be not, then the ſame ſhall be done in the market towne lying neareſt to the ſayd heritages, within the iuriſdiction and precincts of the iudiciall ſeat, where deliuerie of ſuch goods is to be made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer into another mans poſſeſſion: and the affixes or billes of ſale ſhall be ſet vpon the poſts in the ſaid market, and at the entrance of the iudgement hall in the ſaid place, and by this meanes the ſaid cries of ſale ſhall ſtand good and effectuall, and proceede ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the contents and meaning of the decree, not being adiudged amongſt the courſes that are croſſed and diſanulled, howſoeuer they might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged againſt the ſame, to that end and purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="part">
               <head>LXIX</head>
               <p>All titles, papers, euidences, and inſtruments, which haue bene taken, ſhall be reſtored and giuen backe againe, both on the one ſide and on the other, vnto them vnto whome they appertaine, although the ſaid papers, or the Caſtles and houſes wherein they were kept, haue bene taken and ſeazed vpon, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſpeciall commiſſions from the laſt deceaſed king our moſt honorable Lord and brother in law, or from our ſelfe, or by the commandement of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4143:25"/> Gouernours and Lieutenants generall of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, or by the authority of the chiefe and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall on the other ſide, or vpon what other pretext &amp; colour ſoeuer it may be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="part">
               <head>LXX</head>
               <p>Their children which haue withdrawne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues out of our kingdome, at any time ſince the death of the deceaſed king <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, our moſt honourable Lord &amp; father in law, for the cauſe of Religion and of the troubles, although that the ſaid children be borne out of the Reame, ſhall be held and accompted for naturall Frenchmen, and as inhabiting and dwelling in our kingdome, and we haue declared and do declare them to be ſuch, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuyng out of any writs of naturalization, or any other warrant from vs, then this preſent Edict, all maner of ordinances contrarie hereunto notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which we haue abrogated &amp; do abrogate: and yet we charge and command, that the ſayd chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren born in ſtrange countreys, ſhal be bound with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ten years after the publiſhing of this preſent E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict to come and dwell in this our Realme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="part">
               <head>LXXI</head>
               <p>Thoſe of the ſaid pretended reformed Religion, and others which haue followed that ſide, which had taken to farme any Offices, Land, Toll, forraine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and other rights belonging vnto vs, and haue not bene able to inioy the ſame becauſe of the troubles, ſhall ſtand diſcharged, and we do diſcharge them of that which they haue not receiued of the ſaid farmes, or which without any fraude they haue
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4143:26"/> paid elſewhere, then into the receipts of our Fine of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, all maner of obligations paſſed by them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe matters notwithſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="part">
               <head>LXXII</head>
               <p>All maner of places, cities and Prouinces of our Realme, Countreys, Lands and Dominions, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beiſſance vnto vs, ſhall vſe and enioy the ſame priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, immunities, liberties, freedomes, faires, markets, iuriſdiction and ſeats of Iuſtice, which they vſed and enioyed before the troubles began, in the moneth of March in the yeare 1585. and others go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before: all letters to the contrary, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer tranſlations of any of the ſaid iudiciall ſeats not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding: prouided that they haue bene done onely vpon the occaſion of the troubles: which ſeats of Iuſtice ſhall be reduced and reeſtabliſhed in the cities and places where they were before time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="part">
               <head>LXXIII</head>
               <p>If there be as yet anie priſoners which are held by authority of Iuſtice or otherwiſe, as namely in the galleys, vpon the occaſion of the troubles, or of the ſaid Religion, they ſhall be enlarged and ſet at full libertie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="part">
               <head>LXXIIII</head>
               <p>Thoſe of the ſaid Religion ſhall not hereafter be ſurcharged or ouer borne with any maner of charges ordinarie or extraordinarie, more then the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, &amp; according to the proportion of their goods and abilitie: and as for ſuch as do find themſelues o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercharged, they ſhall haue their redreſſe before the Iudges, to whome the examination of ſuch matters
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4143:26"/> doth appertaine. And all our Subiects as well thoſe of the Catholike, as thoſe of the pretended refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion, ſhall indifferently be diſcharged of all charges which haue bene impoſed vpon the one ſide or vpon the other, during the troubles, by them which were of the contrarie partie and not conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. And ſo in like maner of debts ariſing and gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing due but not paid, and of the coſts and charges defraied &amp; laid out without their conſent. But there ſhall not anie demand be made of the fruites which ſhall haue bene imployed in the paiment of the ſaid charges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="part">
               <head>LXXV</head>
               <p>Our meaning likewiſe is not that thoſe of the ſaid Religion and others which haue taken partie with them, neither yet that the Catholikes which were dwelling in the cities and places by them forcibly held and taken, and were made to contribute to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may be ſued for the paiment of the taxes, ſubſidies, graunts, great fifteenes, litle fifteenes, toles, repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and other impoſitions and helpes falling, &amp; impoſed vpon them during the troubles happening before, &amp; vnto our comming to the Crowne, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be by the Edicts and Preceptes of the decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Kings our Predeceſſours, or by the aduice and counſell of the Gouernours and Eſtates of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, Courts of Parliament and other Courts: we haue diſcharged and acquited &amp; do diſcharge and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite them, forbidding our generall Treaſurers of Fraunce and of our Fine Offices, our Receiuers, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and particular, their commiſſioners, &amp; bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4143:27"/> and others the attendants &amp; Commiſſioners of our Fine offices, to ſearch, moleſt, or diſquiet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly in any maner of ſort whatſoeuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="part">
               <head>LXXVI.</head>
               <p>All Dukes, Lords, Knights, Gentlemen, incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Cities, and Communalties, and all others which haue aided and releiued them, their widowes, heyres, and ſucceſſors ſhall ſtand quit and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of all moneyes by them taken and leuied, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the kings money to what ſumme ſoeuer it might amount, or of thoſe raiſed of the Citie, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munalties &amp; particular perſons, of rents, reuenewes, plate, the ſale of the mouables of Eccleſiaſticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and others, timber, trees, whether they were of demaine or others, amercements, booties, ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, or monies of any other nature whatſoeuer, by them taken vpon the occaſion of the troubles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne in the moneth of March 1585. and the other troubles going before, euen vnto our comming to the Crowne, ſo that neitheir they nor thoſe which ſhall haue bin by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> committed &amp; ſet on worke for the leuying of the ſayd moneyes, or which haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or furniſhed them therewith by their ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhall be any manner of way ſearched or inquired after, either for the preſent or in any other time to come, and both they and their Commiſſioners ſhall ſtand quit &amp; diſcharged of all maner of ordering &amp; diſpoſing of the ſaid moneys, bringing of al maner of diſcharges (within foure moneths after the publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this preſent Edict, made in the court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Paris</hi>) acquittances iuſtly &amp; truly obtained of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:4143:27"/> the heads of them of the religion, or of them which ſhall haue bene by the ſayd leaders and heads made Commiſſioners to audit and take the accompts, or of the communalties of the Cities, which haue had commandement and charge during the ſayd trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. They ſhall likewiſe ſtand acquitted of all feates of hoſtilitie, leauies and conducts of ſouldiers, coyning and rating of moneyes, made according to the appointment of the ſayd heads and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunders, melting and taking of artillery and munitions, making of gun-pouder and ſalt-peter, taking, fortifying, diſmantling and ouerthrowing of Cities, Caſtles, Boroughes, and hamlets, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts made vppon the ſame, burnings and pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings downe of Churches and houſes, eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of Iuſtice, iudgements, and executing of the ſame, whether it were in ciuill matters or criminall, rule and gouernment framed amongſt themſelues, voyages, intelligences, traficke, treaties &amp; contracts made with all ſtraunge Princes and communalties, and bringing in of the ſayd ſtrangers into the Cities and other places of our Realme, and generally of all that which hath bene done, acted, geſted, and traded during, the ſaid troubles ſince the death of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, our moſt Honourable Lord and Father in Law, by them of the ſayd Religion, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which haue taken parties with them, although that it ought to be particularly expreſſed and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="part">
               <head>LXXVII.</head>
               <p>Thoſe alſo of the ſayd relgion ſhall ſtand diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of all both generall and prouinciall aſſemblies,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:4143:28"/> by them made and holden either at <hi>Mante,</hi> or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in anie other place, vntill this preſent, in like maner of counſels eſtabliſhed by them, and ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the prouinces, conſultations, ordinances, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and directions giuen to the ſaid aſſemblies and Counſels, ſetting and augmenting of garriſons, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering of ſouldiers, leauying and taking of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes, were it in the hands of our Receiuers general or particular, collectors of pariſhes, or otherwiſe in what maner ſoeuer it were, iudgement vnder ſeale, continuance or new eſtabliſhing of treaties, &amp; toles &amp; the receipt thereof, namely at <hi>Roan,</hi> and vpon the riuer of <hi>Charante, Garonne,</hi> of <hi>Roſne</hi> and <hi>Dordone,</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories and fights by Sea, fortifications of cities, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and places, impoſitions of mony, borowing &amp; receipt of the ſaid moneys, diſplacing of our Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and Farmers, and other officers, the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of others in their places, and of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of marches, vnions, and trades made as well within as without our Realme: and generally of all that which hath bene done, deliberated, written and ordained by the ſaid Aſſemblies and Counſels. Thoſe which haue giuen their aduiſe, ſigned &amp; exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, cauſed to ſigne and execute the ſayd ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, rules &amp; conſultations, not being to be ſearched or inquired after, neither yet their widowes, heires, or ſucceſſors, for the time preſent, nor any time here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to come: howſoeuer euerie of the particulars be not here full ſet downe and declared: and as for our Atturneyes generall, their ſubſtitutes, and all thoſe which might pretend anie intereſt or dealing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4143:28"/> therein by any maner of meanes whatſoeuer, we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne them perpetuall ſilence in all and euerie one of the ſaid points: all iudgements ſentences, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, informations &amp; proceedings to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie notwithſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="part">
               <head>LXXVIII.</head>
               <p>We further approue, ratifie and authoriſe the accounts which haue bene, heard, taken and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Deputies of the ſayd aſſembly, and we will that they, as likewiſe their acquittances and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars which haue bene giuen vp by accomptants, be caried into our court of Accounts of <hi>Paris,</hi> three moneths after the publication of the preſent Edict, put into the hands of our Atturny generall to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to the <hi>Cuſtos Rotulorum</hi> and Regiſters of our ſaid court, there to haue recourſe vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwayes, or ſo oft as neceſſity ſhall require, and there ſhal not be any refuſing or denying to receiue the ſaid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts: neither yet any cauſe of commanding the ſaid Accomptants to appeare or in anie ſort to be puniſhed, except in caſe of omitting &amp; leauing out of ſome receits, and foiſting in of falſe acquittances: Commanding our Atturney general to ſay nothing about the remainder, or that which is behind, or about their order and maner of proceeding, as not hauing bene well and ſufficiently looked vnto. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding the people, &amp; men imployed in our courts of Accounts, as well of <hi>Paris,</hi> as of other prouinces where they are eſtabliſhed, to take any acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame, in anie ſort or manner whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="part">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:4143:29"/>
               <head>LXXIX.</head>
               <p>And as for the accounts that haue not as yet bin giuen vp, our will is, that they ſhold be audited, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and examined by the Commiſſioners which ſhall be deputed by vs thereunto: and they without making any ſcruple, ſhall paſſe the ſame, allowing all ſuch parties payd by the ſayd Comptants, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the ordinances of the ſaid Aſſembly, or others hauing power and auhoritie thereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="part">
               <head>LXXX.</head>
               <p>All Collectors, Receiuers, Farmers, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhall ſtand well and truly diſcharged of all the ſummes of moneyes which they haue paid to the ſaid Commiſſioners of the ſaid Aſſembly, of what nature ſoeuer they be, vnto the laſt day of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. And we will that all ſhalbe paſſed and allowed for accounts, which ſhalbe giuen vp in our courts of Accounts neatly and ſimply, by vertue of acquittan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which ſhall hereafter be brought in: and if any were afterward diſpatched or deliuered, they ſhall ſtand as none: and thoſe which ſhall accept of, or deliuer them ſhall be condemned in an amerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of falſe imployment. And whereas there haue bene already accounts giuen vp, vpon which there ſhould haue fallen ſome charges, we haue for this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration taken away &amp; eaſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame, &amp; haue reeſtabliſhed, &amp; do reeſtabliſh the ſaid perſons fully by vertue of theſe preſents: &amp; there ſhall not anie particular letters, or any other thing then the copie of this preſent article be demanded or requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them, for that which hath paſſed before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:4143:29"/>
               <head>LXXXI.</head>
               <p>The Gouernours, Captaines, Conſuls, and other perſons put in commiſſion for the taking vp of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes to pay the garriſons of places holden by them of the ſaid religion, and whom our pariſhionall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers &amp; Collectors haue furniſhed by loane vpon their bils and obligations, whether it were by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, or by warrant and commandement from the generall Treaſurers, the moneyes neceſſarie for the maintenance of the ſaid garriſons, vnto the iumping &amp; falling in of that which was brought and wrought by the eſtate which we haue cauſed to be addreſſed in the beginning of the yeare 1596. and the aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation and enlargement afterward graunted by vs, ſhall be held quitted &amp; diſcharged of that which hath bin payd for the fact aboue ſpecified, although there be no expreſſe mention made thereof in the ſayd billes and obligations: which ſhal become vnto them as nothing: and for the ſatisfying thereof, the generall treaſurers in euerie their generalitie ſhall cauſe to be directed vnto the ſaid Collectors, by the particular Treaſurers their acquittances: and by the generall Receiuers their acquittances to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Receiuers, and the diſcharge of ſuch generall Receiuers, ſhall be the ſummes which they haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vp in account, in ſuch ſort as hath bene ſayd, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſed vpon the precepts giuen out by the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of ſcarſity, vnder the names of the generall Treaſurers extraordinary of our warres, for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſayd garriſons. And wheras the precepts ſhall not amount to ſo much as our ſaid eſtate and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:4143:30"/> augmentation of the yeare 1596. beareth, we or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine that there be diſpatched and ſent out new pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, concerning that which is wanting, for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of thoſe which ſtand countable to vs, and for the making of reſtitution of thoſe promiſes and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations, in ſuch ſort as that there may not remaine any thing to be demaunded hereafter of them which haue thereby engaged themſelues, and that all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of writs or letters of allowance that ſhall be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for the diſcharge of thoſe which do ſtand countable, be diſpatched and graunted by vertue of this preſent article.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="part">
               <head>LXXXII.</head>
               <p>Againe, thoſe of the ſaid religion ſhall leaue off and ſurceaſe from henceforth all maner of practiſes, trafficke, and intelligences, as wel within as without our realme: and the ſaid aſſemblies and Counſels e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed within the prouinces, ſhal ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and breake vp with ſpeede: and all leagues &amp; aſſociations already made or to be made, vpon what color or pretext ſoeuer it may be, to the preiudice of our preſent Edict, ſhall be razed and diſanulled, as we do raze and diſanull them: expreſly forbidding all our ſubiects hereafter to make any concurſes, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyings of moneys, without our leaue &amp; licenſe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications, billing or banding of men, congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and aſſemblies, other then thoſe which are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by our preſent Edict, and without armes. And this we forbid &amp; forewarne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, vpon paine of being moſt ſeuerely puniſhed, &amp; as contemners and breakers of our precepts and ordinances.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="part">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:4143:30"/>
               <head>LXXXIII</head>
               <p>All Prizes that haue bene taken at Sea during the troubles, by vertue of licenſe or letters of Mart gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and all ſuch robberies as haue bin made by land, vpon them of the contrarie partie, and which haue bene determined by Iudges and Commiſſioners of the Admiraltie, or by the head and chiefe of them of the Religion, or their Counſell, ſhall lye dead and ſmoothered vnder the benefit of our preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Edict, it not being permitted, that they ſhould commence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſute for the ſame: neither ſhall the Captaines which haue taken the ſaid prizes, their ſureties, the ſaid Iudges and Officers, their wiues and heires, be ſearched or inquired after, neither moleſted in anie maner of ſort, all Iudgements of our priuie Counſel and Parliaments, and all letters of Mart and ſeazures depending and not iudged (whereof we will haue them to be fully and wholly eaſed and ſet free) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="part">
               <head>LXXXIIII</head>
               <p>In like maner thoſe of the ſaid Religion ſhall not be ſearched or inquired after, for the reſiſtances and impeachments by them committed heretofore, and thoſe ſince the troubles ended in the execution of iudgements and iudiciall ſentences, graunted and giuen out for the reeſtabliſhing of the Catholike A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike, Romiſh Religion, in diuerſe places of this Realme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="part">
               <head>LXXXV</head>
               <p>And as concerning whatſoeuer hath bene done or taken during the troubles, either without any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:4143:31"/> of hoſtilitie, or by way of hoſtilitie, contrarie to the publike or particular orders &amp; appointment of the heads and chiefeſt perſons, or the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties of the Prouinces which had commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it ſhall be lawfull to ſue for the redreſſe of the ſame by way of Iuſtice</p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="part">
               <head>LXXXVI</head>
               <p>In as much neuertheleſſe as that if ſuch things as haue bene done contrary to the rules and good orders eſtabliſhed, both on the one part and on the other, be indifferently excepted and reſtrained from being within the benefite of the generall pardon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by our preſent Edict, and ſtand ſtill ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to be ſearched and inquired after, there beno ſouldier, but that he may be adiudged to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whereupon might enſue a renuing of troubles: For this cauſe we will and ordaine, that only the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and execrable caſes and miſdemeanours ſtand excepted from the benefite of the ſaid pardon, as namely rapes and rauiſhing of wiues and maides, burnings and conſumings by fire, murthers and robberies committed by trecherie, and wilfully, and that not in the feats of hoſtilitie, but vpon ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular grudge and contrarie to the lawes of armes, infringing and violating of paſſeports and protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with the committing of murther and pillages without anie warrant, in reſpect of them of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and others which haue taken the part of ſuch as were the chiefe, and had authoritie ouer them, grounded vpon particular occaſions which did mooue them to commaund and ordaine the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="part">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:4143:31"/>
               <head>LXXXVII</head>
               <p>We ordaine likewiſe, that the puniſhing of crimes and treſpaſſes committed amongſt men of the ſame ſide and partie, (if it be not in ſuch caſes and deedes as they were enioyned to do by the chiefe of the one ſide and of the other, according to the neceſſitie, Lawes and Orders of armes) ſhall be looked vnto &amp; executed: and as concerning the leuying and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of moneys, bearing of armes, and other feats of warre grounded vpon priuate authoritie and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good auouch, it ſhall be proſecuted by way of Iuſtice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="part">
               <head>LXXXVIII</head>
               <p>The ruines and razings of Cities diſmantled du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the troubles, may by our permiſſion be reedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and repaired by the inhabitants, at their coſts &amp; charges, and the prouiſoes graunted heretofore to that end, ſhall hold and haue place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="part">
               <head>LXXXIX</head>
               <p>We ordaine and will, and it pleaſeth vs, that all the Lords, Knights, Gentlemen and others, of what qualitie or condition ſoeuer they be, of the ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reformed Religion, and others which haue taken partie with them, do reenter and become effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually conſerued in the enioying of all and euery part of their goods, rights, titles, accompts, dignities and actions, the Iudgements following in the times of the ſaid troubles and by reaſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of notwithſtanding: the which iudgements, ſeazures and definitiue ſentences, and whatſoeuer elſe ſhold
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:4143:32"/> haue enſued, we haue to this end, declared and doe declare, to be none, and of no effect and value.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="part">
               <head>XC</head>
               <p>The purchaſes that thoſe of the pretended refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion and others which haue taken partie with them, (haue they done it by the authoritie of anie others then of the deceaſed Kings our Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours,) if they be any of the immoueables belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the Church, ſhal take no place or effect. But rather we graunt and will, and it pleaſeth vs, that the ſaid Church-men reenter incontinently and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay, and be conſerued in the poſſeſſion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al enioying of the ſaid goods ſo aliened, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bound to reſtore the prices of the ſaid ſales: and that (notwithſtanding the ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracts of ſale, which to that effect we haue razed out &amp; reuoked as none, and ſo alſo, as that the ſaid purchaſers ſhall not haue any redreſſe or reliefe by courſe of law, of them which were the Chiefe, and by whoſe authoritie the ſaid goods haue bene ſold) may yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding get into their purſes againe, the moneys that they haue truly and without fraud disburſed, there ſhall be graunted out our letters patents of permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to them of the ſaid Religion, to impoſe &amp; make euen vpon them the ſummes whereunto the ſaid ſales ſhall amount, and the purchaſers of the ſaid goods may not pretend any action for their dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges &amp; intereſt, for lack of the enioying of them: but rather they ſhal be content with the reſtoring of the money laid out by them for the price of the ſayd
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:4143:32"/> purchaſes, reckening for part of paiment of the ſaid price, the fruits by them reaped thereupon, in caſe that the ſaid ſale be found to be made at a verie low and vniuſt price.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="part">
               <head>XCI.</head>
               <p>And to the end that aſwell our Iuſtices and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, as other our ſubiects, may be clearely and with all aſſurance aduertiſed of our will and intention, &amp; to take away all vncertainties and doubts, which might ariſe by reaſon of the former Edicts, through the diuerſe variableneſſe that is in them, we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and do declare, all other the former Edicts, ſecret Articles, letters, declarations, qualifications, reſtraints, interpretations, iudgements, and inrole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as well ſecret as other conſultations hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made by our ſelfe or others our predeceſſors, in our Courts of Parliament and elſewhere, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the matter of the ſayd Religion, and troubles cauſed in our ſaid Realme, to be of no effect and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue; which together with the things therein annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated and diſanulled, we haue by this our preſent E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict abrogated and diſallowed, and do abrogate and diſallow, and from henceforth (as then we did) race, reuoke, and diſanull them: expreſly declaring that we will that this our Edict be firme and inuiolable, kept and obſerued, as well by our ſayd Iuſtices and officers, as other our Subiects, without leauing or hauing any regard vnto all that which might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary or derogatorie vnto it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="part">
               <head>XCII.</head>
               <p>And for the ſtronger aſſurance of the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:4143:33"/> &amp; obſeruing of the ſame, as we deſire it ſhold, we will, ordaine, and it is our pleaſure, that all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors and Lieutenants generall of our Prouinces, Baylifs, Lieutenants ſpecial, and other ordinary Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Cities of our Realme, preſently after the receipt of the ſayd Edict, do cauſe it to be obſerued and kept, euery one in his place: as alſo the Mayors, Eſchetors, Conſuls and Iurats of Cities, aſwell thoſe that continue but one yeare, as thoſe that are perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. We likewiſe enioyne our ſayd Baylifs, Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours or their deputies, and other Iudges, to take an oath of the chiefe inhabitants of the ſayd Cities, as well of the one as of the other Religion, for the maintaining of the preſent Edict, incontinently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the publiſhing of the ſame: taking al them of the ſayd Cities into our protection and ſafegard, and commending the one to the good obſeruing and and marking of another, and charging them reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely and by publike actes to aunſwere and curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly fulfill our requeſts, in diſcouering the reſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which ſhall bee made againſt or in our ſayd E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict within the ſayd Cities, by the inhabitants of the ſme, or elſe to preſent and bring before the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices the ſayd reſiſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="part">
               <head>XCIII.</head>
               <p>We commaund our louing friends, and faithfull people, keeping our Courts of Parliament, Courts of accompts, and Courts of Aides, that incontinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the preſent Edict receiued, they let al maner of things ceaſe, and vpon paine of hauing whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they ſhall continue to do diſanulled, to take the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:4143:33"/> like oath as aboue, and to cauſe the ſame our Edict to be publiſhed and inrolled in our ſayd Courts ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the forme and tenour of the ſame, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely and ſimply, without vſing of any manner of qualifications, reſtraints, declarations, or ſecret re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters, and that without expecting or looking for any other prouocation or commandement from vs: and of our Atturneys general, incontinently, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay, to require and put in practiſe the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="part">
               <head>XCIIII.</head>
               <p>So likewiſe we giue in charge to our ſayd Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and officers of our ſayd Courts of Parliament, Courts of Accompts, and Courts of Aides, Baylifs, Gouernours, Prouoſts, and others our Iuſtices and officers to whom it ſhall belong, and to their depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that they cauſe to be read, publiſhed &amp; enregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred this our preſent Edict and Ordenance in their Courts and iuriſdictions, and the ſame to keepe, maintaine, and obſerue from point to point, and to cauſe all them whom it concerneth, to enioy and vſe whatſoeuer contained in the ſame in all full, ample and peaceable maner, ſtaying and ceaſing and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to ſtay and ceaſe all troubles &amp; impeachments to the contrary: for ſuch is our will and pleaſure. In witneſſe wherof we haue ſigned theſe preſents with our owne hand, and vnto the ſame, that ſo they may become a firme and ſtable thing for euer, cauſed our ſeale to be ſet &amp; put. Giuen at <hi>Nantz</hi> in the moneth of Aprill, and in the yeare of grace 1598. And of our Raigne the ninth.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:4143:34"/>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Signed. <hi>Henry.</hi>
                  </signed>




               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>By the king ſitting in this Counſell.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Forget.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
               <postscript>
                  <p>And vpon the ſide.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Viſa.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
               <postscript>
                  <p>And ſealed with the great ſeale, with greene waxe, vpon a ribond of red and greene ſilke.</p>
                  <p>Read, publiſhed, and enregiſtred, yea and that the Atturney generall for the king at <hi>Paris</hi> in the Parliament the xxv. of February 1599. conſenting thereunto.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Signed. <hi>Voyſin.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Reade, publiſhed and regiſtred in the Court of Accompts, yea and that with the conſent of the Atturney generall of the king. The laſt day of March 1599.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Signed. <hi>De la Fontaine.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Read, publiſhed, and regiſtred, and yea that the kings Atturney generall conſenting thereto, at <hi>Paris,</hi> in the Court of Aides, the thirtieth of Aprill 1599.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Signed. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:4143:34"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
